是的，我们不是很好。
Yeah, we're not so good.
好的，那 Erica 呢，
Good, how about Erica,
lazy 实验对你来说怎么样。
how's the lazy lab for you.
我也觉得还可以，
I also thought it was okay
我也是在 copyin 和 copyout 有 bug ，
and I also had a bug with the copyin and copyout,
但我得到了结果，所以，还可以。
but I got that result, so yeah.
我想这是一种棘手的情况，
I think it is one of those tricky cases
当你开始编程的时候，可能没有想到。
that you might not think about when you start programming.
但是，幸运的是， usertests 会为你找到它。
But, luckily usertests will find it for you.
Caroline 。
The, Caroline.
实验进行得很顺利，
The lab is going good,
实际上我还没有做完。
I haven't finished yet actually.
好的，我想要注意 copyin 。
Alright, worry about copyin, I guess.
是的。
Yeah.
Kendall Garner 怎么样？
How about Kendall Garner?
我想在很大程度上，
I think for the most part of the,
对我来说不算太糟，
it was not too bad for me,
可能试着解决的最奇怪的[]是，
probably the weirdest [] was trying to figure out
当它低于堆栈的界限。
when it went below bounds of the stack.
是的，应该是它到达了守护页。
Yeah, it to the guard page basically.
好的。
Good.
好的，差不多该开始了。
Okay, well it's about time to get started.
欢迎来到 6.S081 的下一节课，
So welcome to the next lecture, in the 6.S081,
无论你在哪里，不管是什么时区。
wherever you are, whatever time zone.
所以，今天的课程是关于锁。
So today's lecture is about locks.
你们可能在之前的课上见过锁，
You probably have seen locks in previous classes,
或者至少以这样或那样的方式与它们接触，
or at least being in touch with them in some way or another,
这节课是有点概念性的课程，
and so this lecture a little bit of a conceptual lecture,
可能与你之前见过的一些东西有些重叠，
may overlap a little bit with some things you've seen before,
锁将更关注内核和操作系统方面。
locks will have a little bit more of kernel and OS [focus].
这改变了几件事情。
And that changes a couple things.
作为开始，
Just to get started,
让我们提醒自己，为什么需要锁，
let's remind ourselves why we need locks,
我想我们的出发点是，
you know I guess the starting point is really that
应用程序想要使用多个核心。
applications well want to use multiple cores.
它们希望使用多核来获得性能。
They want to use multiple cores to get performance.
所以，如果一个应用程序希望在多个核心上运行，
And so if an application actually want to run on multiple cores
可能核心是应用程序调用系统调用的一部分，
and [presumably] what's the cores are part of the application may invoke system calls
所以内核必须能够处理，
and so the kernel must be able to handle,
必须处理并发系统调用。
must handle parallel system calls.
这意味着系统调用在不同的核心上并行运行，
And that means that you know the system calls run in parallel on different cores,
它们可能并行访问共享数据结构。
they may actually access shared data structures, data structures in parallel.
就像你们已经在 alloc 看到过的，
And as you've seen by the alloc,
实际上 xv6 有相当多的共享数据结构，
actually xv6 ask quite a number of shared data structures
比如 proc 数据结构或 ticks ，
what's the proc structures or you know ticks
或者稍后我们会看到缓冲区，
or you know later we'll see the buffer cache,
实际上有大量的共享数据结构。
you know there's actually a ton of shared data structures.
所以，如果你并行访问一个数据结构，
And so if you have parallel access you know to a data structure
其中一个核心是写入者，
in one of the cores are writer
其他是读取者，
and the other cores are reader
我们阻塞来协调更新这些共享数据结构，
you know we basically blocks to coordinate these updates to shared data structure,
这样读取者看到一致的。
so that readers see consistent view.
所以我们需要锁，来控制共享，保证正确共享。
So we need locks, you know to, for control sharing, for correct sharing.
现在，这有点令人沮丧。
Now, this is some sence a little bit of a bummer.
因为我们想要并行访问，
Because we want these parallel access,
我们想在不同的核心上并行运行多个一致的调用，
we want to run multiple consistent calls in parallel on different cores,
但不幸的是，如果它们共享数据结构，
but unfortunately, if they share data structures,
它们需要锁，
you know they need locks,
而锁序列化操作，
and locks you know serialize basically operations
所以，实际上，锁最终会限制性能。
and so in fact you know locks in the end can limit performance.
所以我们现在的情况有些微妙，
And so we're sort of in a tricky situation,
为了正确，我们需要锁，
where you know for correctness, we need locks,
但对于性能来说，它们不是很好。
you know, but for performance, they're not good.
但是，这就是实际情况，
But you know there's going to be a fact of life
我们看看能做些什么。
and we'll see what can do about it.
但这是最高级别的场景，
But that's sort of the top level scenario here
也许带来了这一点，
and you know maybe just to really you know brings this point,
为什么应用程序需要多个核心，
why do applications actually want multiple cores
这与技术趋势有关，
and that really has to do with you know technology trends,
在过去的几十年里，
you know over the last couple decades,
有一些经典的图表，
and you know there's sort of this classic graphs,
在某种程度上说明了这些观点，
that sort of make these points,
所以，让我调出其中一个，
so let me pull up one of them,
这是一个有点复杂的图表，
there's a little bit of a complicated graph,
x 轴上是年份，
you know there's years on the x axis
而 y 轴上是单位，
and y axis, there's you know units
或者根据我们看哪条线是不同的单位。
or different types of units depending on which line we're looking at.
但是真正的东西是，
But the thing that really look at, it is that,
过去几年发生的事情。
what has happened in the last couple years.
过去几十年是，
The last decades is that,
从 2000 年开始，
so starting in the two thousands,
时钟频率并没有继续增加。
that the clock frequency hasn't really increased any more.
基本上是停滞不前，持续不变的。
So basically this has plateaued, constant.
所以，核心的单线程性能，
And as a result, basically single thread performance of core
也基本达到了极限，停滞不前。
also basically has reached limit you know plateaued.
然而，另一方面，
And yet on the other hand,
核心的最小晶体管数量还在随时间增长，
the minimum cores of the number of transistors still has been increasing over the same time period,
所以，如果你不能使用晶体管使单个核心运行得更快，
so if you can't like you know use transistors to make a single core sort of run faster,
唯一的选择是使用多个内核，
you know the only other option basically have to have multiple cores
你可以看到从 2001 年或 2000 年开始，
and you see indeed that starting from 2001 or from nearly 2000,
内核的数量越来越多。
the number of cores has gone up.
所以，应用程序需要更高的性能，
And so there's an application wants more performance,
你不能依赖一个核心，
you know, you can't rely on a single core,
而是要使用多个核心。
basically have to through exploiting multiple cores.
而且，这意味着如果应用程序是内核密集型或非内核密集型，
And also, this means if an application is you know kernel intensive or less intensive,
比如一台服务器，
you know a server,
那就意味着操作系统必须在多核上高效运行。
then that means that the operating system also has to be you know run efficiently on multiple cores.
所以这是主要原因，
So that's the main reason,
我们对内核中的并行性非常感兴趣。
you know, we're sort of very interested in parallelism within the kernel.
对这个有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
好的，我猜你们以前看过其中的一些图表，
Okay, I assume, I I assume that you've seen some of these graphs before,
但这很好地提醒我们，
but it's good to remind us
所有讨论的出发点是什么。
what the starting point of all the discussion is.
那么为什么要使用锁，
So why locks,
我们已经提到了，是为了正确性，
you know already hinted at this, you know, they're for correctness,
如果我们有读取者和写入者访问共享数据结构，
if we have you know readers and writers are accessing shared data structure
会出现的问题是，
and you know the thing that goes wrong is,
我们想要避免竞态条件。
we want to avoid race conditions.
如果没有锁，
If you don't have locks,
会出现一种风险，
you know we run the risk,
我们有共享的数据结构，
you know we have shared data structures,
我们会有竞态条件，
that we're going to have, we're going to have race conditions
竞态条件是相当烦人的，
and it turns out that race conditions are pretty annoying,
所以，首先对它的情况有了一点了解，
so justly first got a little bit of sense of what it actually is,
让我们看一下，
let's look at the,
让我们在 xv6 中创造一个竞态条件，
let's create a race condition in xv6
然后看看它是怎么表现出来的，
and sort of see how it actually shows up
然后理解实际发生了什么。
and then understand like what actually happened.
好的，这是 kalloc.c 中的函数 kfree 。
Alright, so here's the function kfree in kalloc.c.
这是一个函数，释放，
You know this is the function that frees,
在你释放页面之后，它会推入到 free 列表，
after you free page, it pushes on the freelist,
内核有一个非常简单的数据结构，
there's kernel has a very simple data structure
使用 freelist 保存所有空闲页表。
to keep the freelist of all free pages.
所以，当 kalloc 需要页面时，它从 freelist 中获取。
So that when kalloc needs to page, that grabbing from the freelist.
这里你可以看到， allocation 有一个，
This you see here, you know the allocation has one,
内存分配器有一个锁 kmem.lock ，
the memory allocator has one lock kmem.lock
在这里，它更新了 freelist ，
and here it actually updates the freelist
使用刚刚释放的页面或者需要释放的参数。
with the page that just has been freed or with argument to free.
所以我们要做的是，
So we're going to do is
注释掉这两个 acquire 和 release ，
like just comment out these two acquire release,
这标志着获得锁，然后释放锁，
that basically mark you know the acquiring of the lock, and then releasing the lock,
所以这段代码，
you know and so this, this, this, this piece of code
之前在中间的这段（代码），
that's in the middle that used to be,
不再是原子地执行了。
there's not more, is not being executed anymore at atomically.
所以我们就这么做，
So let's do that,
然后运行 QEMU ，编译它。
and then run QEMU, so compile it.
在我运行它之前，
And before I run it,
注意到我们已经启动了，
you know notice actually we already booted
实际上，我们已经有几个 kfree 的调用，
and actually presumably we have made some calls probably to kfree,
像你知道的，
and probably as you know,
实际上事情看起来运行得很好。
and so actually things seem to be working fine.
让我们运行 usertests 。
So let's run usertests.
也许要想想这件事，
And maybe you know this interesting to think a little bit about this
你期望的是什么，
and what do you expect,
这能正常工作，或者不能正常工作。
will this work, will does not work.
有人试过吗。
Anybody who tried it out.
我想它可能会丢失一些页面，
I think it could potentially lose some pages,
但也可能不会，
but maybe will not,
因为可能竞态条件不会出现。
because maybe a race condition wouldn't occur.
是的，其中一件事是，
Yeah, so one of the things is
我们面临的是这些情况可能不会发生，
that these we face conditions they might not happen,
所以，让我们运行 usertests ，看看实际会发生什么。
so let's run the usertests and see actually what happens.
我们从这里开始。
So here we started up.
这需要一小段时间，
It'll take a little while,
你可能会抱怨，
as you might complain a little bit,
因为要跑很多，
because you know, run a lot of,
在我的机器上要加载很多，
there are a lot of load on my machine here correct,
这里 QEMU 模拟了三个核心，
you probably know the QEMU simulating three of cores here
并且不同的核心可以并行运行。
and the discrete cores might run in parallel.
到目前为止一切顺利，
And so far so good,
我们开始通过测试。
we're starting to pass tests.
这有点慢，
That's a little bit slower,
因为我同时运行了 Zoom 。
because I'm running zoom at the same time.
让我们稍等一下，看看会发生什么。
Let's wait a couple more and just to see what's going on.
好的，好吧。
Okay, well.
我们还是回去看幻灯片，
Let's just go back to the slides
然后我们过一会再回来看看，
and then we'll check back in a little while
看看会发生什么。
and see what actually happens.
但是需要指出，
But it was pointed out
这些竞态条件可能会出现，也可能不会出现，
you know these race conditions may appear, may not appear, right,
因为情况可能总是这样，
because it's always the case
每个核心或每次我们调用 kfree ，
that every core or every time we call kfree,
这两行（代码）原子地执行，
these two lines are executed atomically
就像它们使用了锁那样，
as they would have done with the lock,
那就不会出现问题，
then there's no problem,
唯一的问题是，
the only problem is
如果两个线程或两个进程同时执行，
if two threads two processes are executed at the same time
然后有（代码）在中间执行。
and somebody comes in between.
看看这个，在我说话的时候，
Look at this, actually while I'm talking,
我们看到这里有一个 panic ，
we see actually there is a panic
所以，有一些竞态条件引起了 panic 。
and so there's some race condition that can actually cause a panic.
更确切地说，竞态条件会出现，
Rather race conditions that will show up
正如所提到的那样，
as indeed this as mentioned whereas mentioned
这是不够的，
that will show up as [not enough],
一些空闲页面丢失了，
some free pages where some pages get lost,
基本上 usertest 运行得很好直到最后，
so basically usertests runs fine until the very end,
抱怨丢失了一些页面，
where complaints saying well you lost some pages
在整个 usertests 中。
during all user-, all of the [round] usertests.
好的。
Okay.
所以，这些竞态条件可以以不同的方式表现出来，
So these race conditions can show up in different ways,
它们可能会发生，也可能不会发生。
they may happen, they may not happen.
很明显这里发生了，
Clearly something happened here,
让我们试着了解到底哪里出了问题。
let's try to understand you know what actually, what goes wrong.
回到幻灯片上。
Back to the slides.
所以，你知道这个应该在脑海中的图片，
So you know the picture, you should have in your head,
比如有多个核心在运行。
like if there's multiple cores that were running.
所以， CPU0 正在执行指令，
So you know CPU0, CPU0 is executing instructions,
并且 CPU1 也在执行指令。
and CPU1 is executing instructions.
它们都连接到一块内存上，
And they're both connected to a memory,
如果你回想一下方案示意图，
if you're back think back about the scheme schematics,
我们之前展示过几次，
you know we showed a couple times before,
实际上这里有一个 DRAM 控制器，
in fact there's a DRAM controller,
它连接到 DRAM 芯片，
you know that actually connects you know to the DRAM chips,
所有的阶段都在这里，
where all the [stages] living,
或者所有的内存都在这里。
or all the memories living.
我把内存画得大一点，
I'm gonna make that memory a little bit bigger, bigger
好让我有地方可以画，
whatever have some place to draw
所以我们的 freelist 在内存中，
and so basically our freelist, you know lives in, in memory,
我们假设 freelist 上面有两页。
and let's say there's a freelist with two pages on it.
并且两个 CPU 会几乎同时调用 kfree 。
And you know both, both CPUs gonna call kfree roughly at the same time.
好的，再看一下代码，
Okay, so look a little bit at the code, again,
确保运行的跟我们想的一样，
just to make sure that we have running in our heads,
所以我们看看 kfree ，
so we look at kfree,
它传递了 pa ，物理地址，
you know get passing some pa, physical address,
我们要把它放到 freelist 上。
that we're gonna use to actually hook up into the freelist.
CPU0 有一个 R ，
So you know CPU0 has a you know R,
它指向了一些空闲页面，
and that's pointing to some you know free page
可能 CPU1 也有一个，
and maybe yeah and CPU1 has one,
对 CPU1 ，我们使用另一种颜色。
we actually use another color for CPU1.
所以 CPU 另一个 R 总是指向一些页面，
So CPU on another R always pointing to some page,
我们想放入 freelist 。
you know that we want to hook into the freelist.
能理解吗?
Makes sense?
所以，我们回顾代码，
And so you know we're looking back at the code,
所做的第一件事就是，
you know the first thing they do is
更新 r->next 指针指向 freelist 。
you know update r->next pointer to point to the k- to the freelist.
我们假设 CPU1 首先运行，
So let's assume you know that CPU1 runs first
它所做的是，
and you know what it will do is
将指针指向开始，
will put its pointer you know to the beginning of the
指向 freelist 指向的地方。
you know wherever freelist pointed to.
CPU1 也在同时运行，
If you know CPU1 runs exactly at the same time,
然后，它可以在 CPU0 执行第二条指令之前运行，
then, you know it could run before CPU0 executes the second instruction,
所以它可能做同样的事情，
so it actually might do the same thing,
它可能也运行第一条指令，
it might actually also run that first instruction
并且将指针更新为二。
and update and update the pointer to two.
所以，两个 R ，一个来自 CPU1 ，一个来自 CPU0 ，
So both Rs you know one from CPU1, and from CPU zero, one from CPU1
都指向 freelist 的开头，
are pointing to the beginning of the freelist
而 freelist 也指向 freelist 的开头。
and the freelist is also pointing to the beginning of the freelist.
所以，现在有两条指令在并行执行。
So now there are two [remaining] instructions that are being executed in parallel.
所以，我们再回到代码，
So we go back again, you know the code,
剩下的指令正在执行，
the remaining instruction is being executed
更新 freelist 指向 r 。
is actually updating the freelist to point to r.
所以， CPU 0 1 要执行这些指令
And so, you know CPU zero one going to execute these instructions
可能是完全一样的时间，
may be exactly the same, roughly at the same time,
但是有一个会先执行，
but one is gonna go first, correct,
这里只有一个共享内存，
there's only one single shared memory
所以一个更新先执行，
and so one update is going to go first
另一个更新第二。
and the other one is gonna go second.
我们假设 CPU1 先运行。
So let's say CPU one goes first.
现在接下来会发生什么，
And now what will then happen,
好的，首先执行的 CPU ，
well the CPU what goes first,
freelist 会指向它的 R 。
freelist can be pointing to its r, right.
然后 CPU2 运行，
And then CPU two runs,
所以现在 CPU2 运行指令，
so now CPU2 runs actually instruction
那么接下来要做是什么，
and so what is going to do,
它会更新 freelist 指向。
it is going to actually update freelist to point.
这是 freelist ，
So here's a freelist,
它会指向传入的 R 。
and it's actually going point to R that actually passed in.
所以我们现在是一种情况，
And so you know we have a setting now, correct,
我们丢失了一页，
we're, we've lost basically one page,
实际上 CPU0 释放的的 R，
R you know that actually CPU0 actually freed,
最终不在 freelist 上，
actually ended up not being on the freelist at all,
所以我们丢了那一页。
so we lost the page.
一个坏结果出现，
And as one you know bad particular outcome,
当然，可能会有更多的坏结果，
of course there could be more bad outcomes,
因为可能有更多的 CPU 尝试执行这个 freelist ，
because there could be more CPUs actually trying to do this freelist,
它们可能会观察到，
they may observe,
其中之一可能会观察到，
the one of the might observe,
freelist 临时指向 CPU0 的 R ，
the freelist pointing temporarily to CPU0's R,
所以我们开始使用它，
and so we start using that,
然后由第二个 CPU 更新 freelist ，
while then immediately the freelist updated by second CPU,
所以如果引入更多 CPU ，
so that more CPU evolved,
我们可能会得到更离奇的结果，
presumably we could actually get more bizarre outcomes
而不仅是丢失页面。
than just the lost page.
这能理解吗？
Does this make sense?
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
好的。
Okay.
所以，代码使用的方法，
So the way you know as you know the code does,
用来解决这个问题的方法，
you know the way to address this,
是一种很常用的方法，
one way in a very common way,
解决这个问题就是使用锁。
is to address this problem is to use a lock.
所以，让我详细讨论一下锁的问题。
So let me talk a little bit about locks in more detail.
那么什么是锁抽象。
So what is the lock abstraction.
现在它只是一个对象，
Well, now it is just an object,
与内核中的任何其他类型的对象一样，
like any other sort of object in the kernel
任何包含。
and anyone has.
实际上，有一个称为锁结构体的东西，
In fact there's something called struct lock,
它包含一些字段，维护锁的状态，
you know, that has some fields, you know to maintain state about locks,
它有一个相当简单的 API ，
and it has a pretty straightforward API,
有一个 acquire ，
you know there's acquire,
实际上，只有两个对此抽象的调用，
in fact there are only two calls into this abstraction,
acquire 使用一个锁结构体的指针，
which acquire which takes a pointer to lock struct
release 也使用一个锁结构体的指针，
and release you know that actually also takes a pointer lock struct,
来更新锁对象。
to basically update you know the lock object.
这里的规则是，
And basically the rule of [] and the rule here is that,
acquire 遵守以下规则，
the acquire enforces this following rule,
只有一个进程可以进入或者获得锁。
that only one process you know can enter or can acquire the lock.
所以，在任何特定时间点，
So any particular point of time,
只有一个进程
there's only going to be one process
可以成功获取到锁，
that is able to actually successfully acquire the lock
任何在同一时间获取锁的进程，
any other process that basically trying to acquire the lock at the same time,
必须等到第一个进程调用 release 。
has to wait until the first process actually calls release.
所以，这个序列，
And so this sequence,
这些在 acquire release 之间的指令，
you know the instructions, you know between the acquire release,
经常称为临界区间。
are often called the critical section.
被称为临界区间的一个原因是
And one reason is called the critical section is
因为这些指令一起执行，
because this is sort of the the few instruction together to do the
需要对 r 进行更新，
you know need to do the update to r,
由锁保护的任何共享数据结构，
whatever shared data structure, that's protected by the lock
使用原子地方式。
in an atomic fashion.
并且确保，
And ensures that basically,
如果你在 acquire release 之间有多条指令，
if you have multiple instructions in this you know between acquire release,
但它们要么一起执行，要么一个都不执行。
but they all are executed all together or none.
所以，不会出现这种情况，
So there's never a case,
临界区的这些指令交错执行，
these instructions in the critical section are interleaved
像我们在竞态条件下看到的那样，
as in the way that we saw in the race conditions
实际上，这用来避免竞态条件。
and actually exactly, that is what avoids these race conditions.
关于锁抽象，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about the lock abstraction?
程序通常有很多锁，
You know programs typically have many locks,
实际上 xv6 就有很多锁。
in fact the xv6 has many locks.
有很多锁的原因是，
And the reason to have many locks is
因为即使，
because you know even though,
锁可以序列化进程的执行，
you know the the lock serializes the execution
两个进入临界区间的进程，
of two processes you know what enter the critical section,
只有一个可以成功，
only one succeeds,
另一个在第一个完成后运行临界区间，
and the other one runs that critical section after the first one finishes,
所以这里没有并行。
so there's no sort of parallelism at all.
如果内核只有一个锁，
So if the kernel had only one lock,
通常称为大内核锁，
which is typically called a big kernel lock,
那么内核中每个系统调用都会被串行化，
then basically every system call in this, in the kernel, would be serialized,
系统调用 1 获取大内核锁，
system call one start gets the one the big kernel lock,
做它想做的事情，
does whatever it needs to do,
然后释放大内核锁，
and then release the big kernel lock
然后返回用户空间。
and then basically returns user space.
然后第二个系统调用运行，
And then the second system call the run,
所以我们有并行运行的程序，
so we have an parellel application,
并行运行大量的系统调用，
that runs, lots of runs system calls in parallel,
突然所有的系统调用都是串行运行的，
suddenly you know all the system calls actually run serially,
如果我们只有一把锁的话。
if we had only one lock.
所以通常程序，比如 xv6 有很多锁，
And so typically your program like, you know xv6 has you know many locks,
因为这样，我们可以得到一些并行性。
because of these, you know we can get some parallelism.
因为，如果两个系统调用使用两个不同的锁，
Because, you know if you know two system calls for example use two different locks,
那么它们实际上可以完全并行运行，
then you know they can actually run a completely parallel,
没有任何串行化，
without any you know serialization,
因为使用不同的锁进行串行化。
because basically you know using different locks serialize.
现在。
Now.
有几点很重要，
There's a couple of important points,
在这个接口中没有什么是强制的，
the nobody really sort of forces in this interface,
你使用 acquire release ，
you know that you put in the acquire release,
这是由程序决定的。
you know it's up to the program to do so.
所以，如果你希望代码段是原子的，
So if you want a particular piece of code to be atomic,
由开发人员将 acquire release 那里。
then it's up to the developer to actually put these acquire release there.
从这里可以清楚地看到，
And there clearly see,
你可以想象，这需要一些技巧性，
you can imagine, that there's a little bit can be tricky,
所以需要认识到，
so it's important to realize that
锁并不是自动完成的，
you know that locking is not actually done automatically for you,
一切都由开发者决定的，
it's all up to the developer to figure out,
将锁与数据结构关联，
to associate locks with data structures
并确保适当的 acquire release 在那里。
and ensuring that the appropriate acquire release are there.
所以，很明显地情况，锁限制了并行性，
So clearly the case, like you know the locks limit in parallelism,
并且因此限制了性能，
and therefore limit performance,
所以，这就提出了何时使用锁的问题。
and so then this raises the question when to lock.
我要给你们一种保守的规则，
And I'm going to give you sort of conservative rule,
但这是考虑这件事的一个很好的起点。
but it's a good one as a starting point to think about things.
所以这个保守的规则，或者叫做指导原则更好，
So the conservative rule, or maybe guidelines is better,
[]是你有两个进程，
[] is that you have two processes,
两个进程访问一个共享数据结构。
two processes access a shared data structure.
其中一个是写入者或更新者，
And one is, one of the them is a writer or an updater
这意味着它对共享数据结构做修改。
so meaning it's actually does modify to share data structure.
那么你需要对这个数据结构使用锁。
Then you need a lock for that data structure.
所以这是一条保守的规则，
So this is a conservative rule,
像是告警的红旗，
sort of like a red flag,
当你编程时，并且有一个由多个进程访问的数据结构，
when you're programming and you have a data structure that is accessed by multiple processes
那么什么是写入者，
and what could be a writer
在这时候，你应该想，
at that point you should be thinking,
好的，这里可能有竞态条件，
okay, there's a possibility of race condition,
你希望避免这种竞态条件，
you want to avoid this you know race condition,
你使用锁，
you stick in a lock,
使用锁来保证这个竞态条件不会发生。
use a lock to guarantee that this race condition can't happen.
但是，这些规则在某些方面太严格了。
But you know those rules in some ways too strict.
在某些情况下，可以处理共享数据结构的这些操作，
There are cases where it's okay to process these actions of shared data structure
其中一个是写入者，
and one is a writer,
特别地是，有一种编程风格称为无锁编程。
in particular, there are styles of programming called lock-free programming.
这是各种会发生的情况。
That actually totally where these kinds of scenarios actually do happen.
无论如何，你想使用无锁编程，
Anyway, you want to lock-free programming
是为了获得更好的性能或更多的并行性。
is basically to get better performance or more parallelism.
无锁编程是很难的，
Lock free program is tricky,
甚至比使用锁编程更难，
even more tricky you know programming of locks,
我们会在本学期末讨论这个问题，
and you know we'll talk about it at the end of this semester,
我们会研究一些无锁编程风格，
we will study some lock-free styles of the programming
特别是在操作系统内核中常见的。
or particularly common in operating system kernels.
基本上，对于这节课以及本学期的剩下的大部分课，
Basically, for this lecture and most of the rest of the semester,
我们会考虑这种情况，
we're going to be thinking about the case,
我们使用锁来控制共享。
we're using locks, you know to control sharing.
这已经很难了，
And that's hard enough,
只用锁，也不是那么简单的。
you know you just use locks, its not that straightforward either.
所以一方面，有点太严格了，
So in one hand, a little bit too strict,
因为并不总是所有情况都需要，
because not always the case that you need
也有一些情况太宽松了。
and also some cases too loose.
如果你可能只是。
If you might just.
你可能[]宽松，
You might [] loose,
你想使用锁，
you want to actually make you know to use locks,
来保证一些其他属性，
you know to enforce some other properties,
比如你看一下 printf ，
like if you look at printf,
如果我们将一个字符串传递给 printf ，
if we pass a string to printf,
xv6 内核试图，
you know the xv6 kernel tries to
至少让整个字符串原子地打印出来。
at least you know get the whole string to be printed atomically.
而且你知道这里不涉及共享数据结构，
And you know there's no shared data structure involved,
但在这种情况下使用锁仍然很有用，
but it's still useful to actually use a lock in that particular case,
因为我们希望输出是串行化的。
because we want the output to be serialized.
所以这个规则并不完美，
So this rule is not perfect,
但它是一个不错的指导原则。
but it's a pretty good guideline.
关于这条规则，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this rule?
我有一个问题不是关于这个规则的，
I had a question not about this rule,
但是有没有可能两个进程同时获取锁，
but isn't it possible that two processes could acquire the lock at the same time
因此可以修改数据结构。
and so would be able to modify the structure.
是的，不是，锁的一部分规定是
Yeah, no, so so part of the sort of contract lock construction is is that
两个进程不能同时获得锁。
it's impossible two process to acquire a lock at the same time.
这条规则，永远不会有这种情况，
If the rule is that there's ever there's no, there's never a case,
两个进程可以同时获得锁，
where two process actually acquire the lock, can hold the lock at the same time,
我们过一会会看到如何实现它，
we'll see in the second, how to implement that,
但是 API 或规范要求是，
but the API or the specification require is,
在任何给定的时间点，只有一个进程或没有持有锁。
there's only one lock holder at any given point in time or zero.
好的。
Yes.
好的，如果我们看一些锁编程，
Okay, so, you know if we see you know programming lock,
可能产生一些问题，因为这些竞态条件。
slightly it could be problematic, because of these race conditions.
当然，那个在 kfree 中的竞态条件，
You know, of course the particular race condition, that we looked at in the kfree
或者是我们在 kfree 中创造的，
or that we created in kfree,
使用一些方法很容易发现，
which were easily spotted in some ways
实际上，如果使用一个竞态检查工具，
and the fact you know if use a race detection tool,
它会立即找到它。
it would immediately find it.
但还有更复杂的情况，
But there are more tricky cases,
你可能会想，为什么可以这样，
so you may wonder like why could use like make,
可以使加锁是自动的？
could make locks or could make locking automatic?
所以，你遵循我刚在说的简单规则，
So you follow this simple rule, that I just stated,
你知道，如果我们每次共享数据结构，
you know then if every we shared data structure,
那么共享数据结构中的操作就需要锁，
then you know operations in that shared data structure basically require lock,
我们应该在每个操作中把锁和数据结构关联起来，
we should associate a lock with the data structure in the every operations,
实际上，它在数据结构上执行，
actually that is, it's performed on that data structure,
来获取或释放锁。
basically acquire or release the lock.
所以考虑它的一种方式是，
So one way to think about it maybe,
在 xv6 术语中，每一种数据结构都有一个锁，
in xv6 terms like every structure you know, has a lock,
这种情况下，锁是自动获取的，
and in that, lock is automatically acquired,
当我们做任何与该结构相关的事情时，
when we do anything related to that struct,
结果发现它太死板了，
it just turns out to be too rigid,
这就是为什么锁不是自动的。
and this is why you know locking can not really be automatic.
所以在运行操作系统中，
So in the operating systems,
比如操作系统如下所示，
for example from an operating system is the following,
假设我们有一个叫 rename 的调用。
let's say we have a call like rename.
它将文件名从一个目录移动到另一个目录，
That moves the filename from one directory to another directory,
假设我们有 d1/x ，
so let's say we have d1/x,
我们把它重命名为 d2/y 。
and we rename it to d2/y.
所以，我们在目录中有文件名 d1/x ，
And so we have the file name in the directory, d1/x,
我们把它重命名为 d2/y 。
and we rename it to d2/y.
所以，如果我们遵循严格的规则，
So the way presumably, if we followed the rigid rule,
比如这个原子锁定规则，会发生什么。
like this rule of atomic locking you know what would happen is.
这条规则，当我们有两个对象，
You know that that rule when we have two objects,
d1 和 d2 。
with d1 and d2.
所以我们遵循规则，原子规则，
And so we follow the rule, then basically atomic rule,
我们对 d1 加锁，删除 x ，然后释放 d1 的锁。
then we lock d1, you know erase x, and release the lock for d1.
然后，我们做数据的第二部分，
And then we do the second part of data,
对 d2 加锁，添加 y ，然后释放 d2 。
you know d2, lock d2, add y, and release d2.
然后我们就完成了。
And then we're done.
这是一种假设的方案，
So this would be the sort of hypothetical schema
你可以想象如果我们进行原子锁会发生什么，
and you imagine what would happen if we did atomic locking,
这个例子的重点是会产生错误的结果，
and the point of this example is going to, will have the wrong outcome
为什么这是一个有问题的方案，
and why, why is this a problematic scheme,
为什么这行不通。
why is this not gonna work.
所以，要考虑的是这个时间。
So, think about like the thing to think about is this period.
所以我们已经完成了第一步，
So we've done the first step, step one,
还没有完成第二步。
not done step, step two yet.
另一个进程会观察到什么。
What could another process observe.
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
文件丢失了。
The file it just be gone.
是的，在第一步和第二步之间，
Yeah, you know this there's between step one and two,
这个文件不存在。
the file doesn't exist.
我的意思是这显然是错误的，
I mean that is clearly wrong,
因为该文件确实存在，它只是被重命名，
because the file does exist, it just being renamed,
应该没有什么时候它不存在，
and never point really that it didn't exist,
但是通过以这种方式实现它，
but by implementing it in this way,
看起来该文件可能并不存在，
it just appears that the file might actually not exist,
尽管它确实存在。
even though it does.
所以正确的解决方案是，
So the really right solution to this is
我们需要的是，
what we need is
在重命名开始前，先锁定 d1 和 d2 ，
that we actually lock d1 and d2 first, at the beginning of rename,
然后擦除并添加，
then erase and add,
然后释放 d1 和 d2 的锁。
and then release the locks for d1 and d2.
所以，这能理解吗？
So, that makes sense?
所以，这是一个例子，
So here's an example
我们有一个需要多个锁的操作，
where we have an operation that acquire needs multiple locks
并且锁不能真正地与这两个对象相关联，
and and the locks cannot really be associated with the two objects,
它们是这个操作的参数，
that are the arguments of this operation,
实际上操作本身必须首先获取两个锁，
it has to be the case that actually the operation itself first requires both locks,
然后执行操作。
then perform the operations.
所以原子锁不是直接可能的。
So there's atomic locking is not directly possible.
会有这种情况，
There's going to be cases,
不是运行简单的方案，
where there's not run to the native scheme
它们会遇到问题。
at those will run into a problem problems.
对这个有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
所以我们能不能这么说，
So could we just say that,
当我们访问数据结构时，
when we're accessing a data structure,
我们需要访问或者我们必须获取
we just have to access or we have to acquire
所有我们需要的数据结构相关联的锁，
all of the locks associated with all of the data structures we need
在开始的时候。
at the beginning.
这是其中之一，
That be one,
是的，这是一种方法，
yeah, so that's one way doing it
我想很快会归结到拥有一个大内核锁。
and I think that we should quickly will come down to basically having a big kernel lock.
好的。
Okay.
你在不会有并发的风险上，
You're on the risk, basically have no parallelism anymore,
所以你想做得更好，
so you want to do better than that right,
我认为这一直是矛盾，
and I think this is always the tension,
你可以使事情变得简单，
you know you can make things simpler
通过使用粗粒度锁，
by basically what's called coarse-grained locking,
但是你会丢失性能，
but then you know you're lose lose performance
或者可能丢失性能，
or you may lose performance,
取决于锁是不是有意的。
depending if the locks intended or not.
好的，谢谢。
Yeah thank you.
从锁的角度来看，这是考虑锁的不同方法。
So lock perspective, so there's different ways to think about locks.
这有三个常见的问题，
You know, those are three common ones,
而且，它们三个都要，
and you know go for all three of them
也许这会帮助你思考锁的问题，
and just maybe that may help you to think about locks
也许其中一个是你的最爱，
and maybe one of them is your favorite
你可以使用它作为你思考问题的方式，
and you can use that one as your way of thinking about it,
但是，这些可能是有用的，
but there's probably helpful to see
它们以不同的方式来思考锁。
that they're actually different ways of thinking about locks.
首先，
So first of all,
可以考虑的一种方式是锁避免丢失更新，
you know one way to think about is actually lock avoid lost updates
或者帮助（避免丢失）。
or help.
如果你正确使用锁，
If you use lock correctly,
锁可以帮助避免丢失更新。
you know locks can help avoiding lost updates.
如果你考虑一下之前的 kalloc.c 中的示例，
And if you think about early example in the kalloc.c,
丢失的更新就是丢失了 kfree 的一个更新。
you know the lost update is basically lose one update to the kfree.
通过使用锁，它没有丢失更新，
And by putting locks, it you know actually didn't lose that update,
所以这是思考这个问题的一种方式，
so that's one way of thinking about it,
一种非常低级的方式。
a very low-level way.
另一种思考方式是，你可以使用锁，
Another way to think about is you know you can make lock,
锁使多步操作成为原子操作。
locks make multi-step operations atomic.
所以，有一种临界区间的观点，
And so there's sort of the view of critical section,
我们使用锁在一系列步骤或指令上，
we have acquire lock with a whole bunch of a steps or instructions,
执行所有指令，然后释放，
executed all instructions, then release,
整个临界区间作为原子操作执行。
basically whole critical section execute as an atomic operation.
这也是思考锁的一个很好的方式。
That sort of also a fine way to think about locks.
然后是第三个，
And then the third one,
这可能会有帮助，
you know that may be helpful,
锁真正的作用是锁帮助维护一个不变量，
is that really what locks do is lock help maintain an invariant,
不变量共享它在保护的数据结构。
invariant share data structure that you know it's protecting.
这里发生的是，
And what was going on is that,
在 acquire 之前，
before acquire,
如果没有锁持有者，持有不变量，
if there's no lock holder, you know that invariant holds,
当我们获得锁，并进行一些操作时，
when we acquire the lock and we do some operations,
那么可能暂时违反不变量，
then temporarily the invariant may be violated,
但是在我们使用 release 的时候，
but at the point that we do the release,
如果你考虑一下 r freelist 的例子，
so if you think about r freelist case,
不变量是空闲指针指向下一个指针，
you know the invariant is you know free pointer points to one other next pointer
并且所有的空闲页面都在一个列表上。
and all the free pages are on a single list.
在这一点上，这是暂时违反的，
And that's temporarily violated at the point,
在 kfree 中间，
in the middle of the kfree,
因为多个指针指向 freelist 的开头。
because like multiple pointers actually point to the beginning of freelist.
然后我们在末尾建立。
And then we [established] at the end of it.
所以如果 freelist 不是那么复杂的变量，
So if where freelist as not so complicated variables,
比如更复杂的共享数据结构，
like more complicated shared data structures,
可以是一种很有帮助的方式，来思考锁到底做了什么。
can be a helpful way of thinking actually what the lock is doing for you.
所以，即使在这三个示例中，
And so see, even in this case three case,
所有三种锁视角都是合理的，
you know all three lock perspective for reasonable perspectives,
它们中的一个，带来了更多思考，
and you know one of them you know brings more [review],
然后，另一个用来考虑锁。
then so, one of the other ones and you use that as your way to think about locks.
对于这一点，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this point?
好的。
Okay.
所以，在我们自己的几件事上，
So in our own for a couple things, sort of,
在[所需]属性中，或者使用锁可能发生的事，
in [desirable] properties or that can actually happen with locks
你知道，锁用来修复正确性问题，避免竞态条件，
and you know like locks are a necessary to fix correctness problem avoids race conditions,
但是当不适当的使用锁，
but locks themselves in when inappropriate inappropriate used,
也会引入它们自己的一套问题。
can also introduce their own set of problems.
所以我想谈一谈这一点，
And so I want to talk a little bit about that
最明显的一个当然是死锁。
and so the obvious one, of course is deadlock.
比如，这个简单的例子，
You know for example, you know the simple case,
虽然有点无聊，但值得一想，
you know a little bit boring, but worthwhile thinking about,
你获取锁，
you know do an acquire you know lock,
你开始了临界区间，
and so you start the critical section
在临界区间内，你又一次获取了同一把锁，
and in the critical section, you do another acquire of the same lock,
接下来会发生什么，
what will happen,
第二次获取能成功吗？
can the second acquire succeed?
好吧，我们早些时候已经说过了，
Well with respect that we've given early on,
你知道这是不允许的，
you know this should be not allowed,
所以第二次获取会被阻塞，
so basically the second acquire must block
直到第一次获取被释放锁，
until the first acquire release lock,
但那是这个进程本身，
but that was you know the process itself,
所以这会导致死锁。
so basically this result in a deadlock.
这是一个微不足道的死锁的例子，
You know, this is a trivial example of deadlock
或许不是很有趣，
and maybe not that interesting,
如果 xv6 [文本]中有一个死锁，
in fact there's a deadlock that xv6 [texts],
因为当它发现相同的进程再次获取相同的锁时，
you know because when it sees that the same process acquire the same lock again,
就会引起 panic 。
actually causes a panic.
一个更有趣的情况是，当涉及多个锁时，
A more interesting cases are when multiple locks are involved,
让我们回到前面的例子，
so let's go to our previous example,
假设我们有以下内容，
let's say we have the following,
我们有核心一号 CPU1 ，
we have core one, maybe CPU1,
我们有 CPU2 。
we have CPU2.
CPU1 执行重命名 d1/x 到 d2/y 。
And CPU1, you know executes rename you know d1/x to d2/y.
并且 CPU2 同时执行，
And CPU2 execute at the same time,
以另一种方式重命名，
rename in the other way,
从另一个方向， d2/a 到 d1/b ，
in the other direction d2/a to d1 you know actually b,
只是为了让名字有所不同。
just to make the names different.
所以这里要注意的关键是，
So the critical of thing to observe here is that
CPU1 运行重命名从 d1 到 d2 ，
CPU1 runs rename from d1 to d2,
而 CPU2 正好相反，
and CPU2 that's exactly the opposite,
执行重命名从 d2 到 d1 。
does rename from d2 to d1.
所以让我们假设，
So let's assume that,
我们是按照它们的参数顺序获取锁的，
we actually acquire the locks in the order of their arguments
那么会发生什么，
and so what will happen correct is that,
在这种情况下，你获得两个锁，
in this case, you will acquire both locks,
我们从前面的一个例子中知道，这上是很重要的。
we know from a previous example that is actually important.
所以获取 d1 锁。
So acquire you know d1 lock.
假设是真正的同时运行，
And you know let's say really run true concurrent,
所以在这一点上，另一个可能，
so at that point, the other guy might actually,
另一个 CPU 可能会先获取 d2 ，
the other CPU might acquire d2 first,
因为这是它的第一个参数。
because you know it's first argument.
而现在 d1 想要获得 d2 ，
And now of course d2, d1 wants to acquired d2,
所以会尝试获取 d2 。
so will try to acquire d2.
它会成功吗，
Will it succeed,
它不会成功，
it won't succeed,
因为另一个持有这个锁，
because the other guy, you know actually has the lock
所以这个会到此为止，不再继续。
and so this guy will stop here and not to proceed.
现在让我们看看另一个 CPU ，
Now let's look at the other CPU,
CPU2 获取了 d2 ，
CPU2 acquire d2,
它现在要获取第二个参数 d1 。
it's now gone acquire d1 for its second argument.
它会试着调用 acquire d1 ，
It's gonna try to call, to call acquire d1,
它是否能够继续执行。
and will it be able to proceed.
不，无法继续，
No, won't be able to proceed,
因为 CPU1 持有锁 d1 。
because the CPU1 actually has the lock d1.
所以有时这被称为死锁，
And so here we're sometimes this is called a deadly embrace,
因为，
you know, where you know,
因为我们获取锁的方式，获取的顺序，
because the way we acquire, the order in which we,
获取锁的顺序会导致死锁。
order which acquire lock results actually in a deadlock.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
这个例子。
This example.
这是一个更危险的死锁的例子，
This is a little bit of a more dangerous example of deadlock,
这不是一个明显的问题，
it's not an obvious problem
这个情况的解决方案是简单的。
and the solution turns out in some sense reasonable simple.
解决方案是，如果你有多把锁，
The solution is that you know if you have multiple locks,
那你就得对锁排序，
then you have to order their locks,
所有操作都必须按照这个顺序来获取锁。
and full operations have to acquire locks in that order.
所以如果你是一名系统设计师，
So if you're a system designer,
你必须决定所有锁对象的全局顺序，
you have to decide you know what the global order is for all lock objects
比如，在这种情况下，
and so for example in this case
你可能会说 d1 应该总是在 d2 之前，
where you may want to say that d1 should always order before d2,
这就意味着，
and that means that,
当我们执行重命名时，
when we execute a rename,
规则是我们总是先获取更小数字的目录，
the rule of life is we always acquire lower number directories first,
在获取更高数字的目录之前。
before we acquire higher order directory number.
这将确保全局顺序，
And that will ensure that basically there's global order
这种情况就不会发生。
and you know this particular case which cannot happen.
因为，锁的顺序会是，
Because you know the lock order is going to be
对于这个是 d1 d2 ，
then for d1 d2 for this guy
这个也使用相同的顺序获取锁， d1 d2 ，
and this guy will acquire locks exactly the same global order, you know, d1 d2
这样我们就没有死锁了。
and then we don't have deadly embrace.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
所以这表明了一些问题，
So this indicates a little bit of problem,
即使这样，
even though like,
好的，让我们来解决这个死锁问题，
okay let's fix this you know this sort of deadlock problem,
我有全局顺序，请注意这个顺序是全局的，
that I have in global order, notice this order is global
这有一个小问题，
and this is an issue a little bit,
在设计系统时，因为。
when designing a system, because.
等一下。
Hold on.
所以考虑一下锁的顺序，
So you think about the sort of lock ordering,
一定是全局的。
you know there has to be sort of global.
所以，如果我们有一个模块 m1 调用方法模块 m2 的方法。
And so we have one module, one m, you know calls method in module two.
那么调用者 m1g ，可能需要注意，
And the caller, you know m1g, you know might actually need to be aware
或者你需要注意，
or could be you need to be aware
在 m2 中 f 获取了哪些锁。
actually what locks f acquire for [one] locks m2 uses.
因为，如果 m2 使用了一些锁，
Because if you know m2 uses some set locks,
然后遵守我们的锁规则，
then you know follow our lock ordering rule,
只需要确保如果它有锁，
[just] got to make sure that you know if it has some locks,
从 f 和 g 获取的所有锁，
then acquires all locks from f and g,
是在某种全局顺序中。
together actually in some global order.
所以这意味着这些内部结构，
And so that really means that these sort of internals,
就锁而言， m2 的内部部件必须对 m1 可见。
internals of m2, in terms of locks must be visible to m1.
所以 m1 可以确保，
So that you know and m1 can ensure that,
以适当的方式调用 m2 。
actually you know calls m2 in the appropriate way.
在某些方面，这是一种对抽象的违反，
And you know in some ways, that is kind of an abstraction violation,
实际上做得很好，
actually work out perfectly
m1 不需要知道关于 m2 实现的任何信息，
and m1 doesn't know need to know anything about how m2 was implemented
不幸的是，锁是一种常见的例子，
and unfortunately locks are common example
m2 要讲内部信息泄露给 m1 ，
of where some of the internals, m2 might actually leak out to m1,
因为 m1 确实需要知道。
because m1 really needs to know.
所以，当你设计一个更大的系统时，
And so when you design a bigger system,
这使得模块化变得更加复杂。
you know, this makes the modularity more complicated.
抱歉，我想知道，是否需要完整的锁的顺序，
Oh sorry, I was just wondering, does need to be a complete ordering of locks
或者有没有一些锁，
or can there be some locks that are,
可以用任何方式排序。
that can be ordered in whatever way they.
是的，这要看情况，
Yeah, it depends,
如果 f 和 g 共享任何锁，
if like f and g you know share any locks right,
比如，如果查看 xv6 ，
for example if you're looking at xv6,
它有多个锁顺序链，
there are sort of multiple strands of lock orderings,
因为有些函数与其他锁无关，
because some functions have nothing to do with other locks
它们永远不会一起获得。
and you know they're never acquired together.
所以如果它们从来没有一起获取，
And so if they're never acquire together,
如果您愿意，只需连接锁集，
just join locks sets, if you will
然后，只需要确保特定锁集合中的顺序是全局的，
and then only you have to make sure that the ordering in one particular locks set is global
并且其它锁集合的顺序序完全独立于其它顺序。
and the ordering the other locks set is completely independent of the other ordering.
所以这是正确的，不一定是全局顺序，
So it is correct, that it doesn't have to be global ordering,
但就像所有操作相同共享类型的锁集的函数，
but like all the functions that manipulate the same share sort of lock set,
它们需要一致的全局顺序。
they need to agree on a global order.
谢谢。
Thank you.
好的，那么。
Okay so.
另一种挑战使用锁的挑战，
One in, you know another sort of challenge with locks,
我们已经看到了两个挑战，
we've seen two challenges,
一个是死锁，一个是模块化，
one is deadlock, one is modularity,
第三个挑战是锁与性能。
the second challenge or third challenge just locks versus performance.
我之前暗示了几次，
And you know really hinted at this a couple times,
但它需要，
but it needs to,
强调一下是非常重要的。
is important enough to actually put some emphasis on.
所以我们想要性能，
And so basically we want to get performance,
你需要拆分数据结构，
you need to split up data structures,
所以如果你有一个大内核锁，
so if you have one big kernel lock,
这将使你的性能限于在单个 CPU 上，
that will limit your performance to basically performance on a single CPU,
如果你想要具有多个 CPU 扩展的性能，
if you want to perform, you want that performed scales with numerous CPUs,
你就得拆分。
you gotta split up.
你需要拆分数据结构。
You need to split up data structures.
最好的拆分，它并不明显，
And best split, you know, it's not obvious
或者是一个挑战，
or can be a challenge,
比如，如果你将锁与每个目录相关联，
you know, for example if you associate the lock with every directories,
如果你将锁与每个 inode 相关联，
if you associate the lock with every inode,
是否将锁与每个进程相关联。
associated lock with every process or not.
哪里是，更适合的以不同的方式拆分数据结构。
Where is the better to, sort of split the data structures in a different way.
如果你需要修改，
And if you make a change,
重新设计锁规则，
you know sort of redesign the locking discipline,
你必须确保，
and you've got to make sure
你仍然保持着不变量，
that you know you're still maintain the invariant,
是内核想要保持的。
that actually the kernels trying to maintain.
如果你拆分锁，
And if you split locks,
你还必须重写代码。
you also have to rewrite the code.
你也可能需要重写代码。
You may have to need, may write, may need to, rewrite code too.
所以事实证明，
And so it turns out that,
你应该重构内核的一部分，或者你的程序的一部分，
basically you should refactor you know part of your kernel or part of your [] program,
为了获得更好的性能，
to get better performance
通过拆分数据结构或引入更多的锁，
by splitting data structure or introducing more locks,
有很多工作要做，
you know there's just a lot of work,
你要仔细考虑，想要维持持的范围，
you have to carefully think through, that maintain, the range that intended to maintain,
你必须要写代码，
you have to [] write code
一般说来，这是一项繁重的工作，
and so generally this is just a lot of work,
它们并不容易。
they're not easy.
所以这是比较负面的观点，
And so there's a little bit of negative view point, right,
因为我们想要更好的性能，
because you know we want to get better performance,
这需要更多的锁。
that suggests you know more locks.
但这是一项繁重的工作。
And, but that is actually a lot of work.
对于这个问题，有一种普遍的做法是，
It's sort of general recipe, you know how to go about this is,
从粗粒度的锁开始，
to you know start of coarse-grained locks,
然后测量。
and then measure.
不管是什么应用程序运行在内核上，
So whatever run a bunch of applications on top of the kernel
观察是否得到了加速，
and see whether you get actually any speedup,
如果它们利用了多个核心。
if they actually exploit multiple cores.
如果它们这样做了，你就完成了，
And if they do, you know you basically be done, right,
你的锁设计已经够好了，
that you're locking design is good enough,
如果没有加快速度，
if you don't get speed up,
这意味着某些锁被争用，
basically that means that some lock is contended,
多个进程尝试获取相同的锁，
multiple processes are trying to get the same lock
因此它们被串行化了，
and therefore they are serialized
所以，得不到加速。
and therefore you don't get speed up.
然后你需要重新考虑，需要重新设计。
Then you know you have to rethink about, then you need to redesign.
但这里的重点是，
But the point is that,
你要以这些测量来指导，
you want to be guided you know by these measurements,
因为可能是这种情况，
because it maybe the case
一些使用粗粒度锁的模块不是经常并行调用，
that you know some module that uses of coarse-grained lock is just not called in parallel often
所以，没有必要对它重新设计，
and therefore it is not necessary to actually redesign,
因为重新设计有很多工作要做，
since redesign there's a lot of work,
这也会使代码的条理变得复杂，
you know can, you know it also can complicate the reasoning about code,
不重新设计这些是一个更好的选择，
you know that, you know it's a good idea not actually do that redesign,
这不是必须的。
it's not necessary.
所以，一般说来，一条好的规则是，
And so, in general, a good rule of form is
从粗粒度的锁开始，
you know start with coarse-grained locks,
测量这些锁中的一个是否出现争用，
measure whether a contention that appears one of these locks
然后重新设计系统的这一部分，
and then redesign that part of the system,
你就会得到更好的并行性。
so that you get better better parallelism.
这能理解吗，目前为止有什么问题吗？
Does that make sense, any questions so far?
好的，我们来看一下。
Okay, let's look at.
好的，让我们看看 xv6 中的一些代码，
Well, let's look at xv6 and you know some code
了解一下，锁在 xv6 中实际是如何工作的。
to understand a little bit how this locking sort of works out in practice the xv6.
所以，我要回到，
And so I'm gonna go back to,
回到这一屏，
to the this screen,
我需要这个。
I really need this.
我想看看 uart ，
And I want to look at uart,
因为我们从那里开始讨论锁。
because we start talking about locking there.
在周一的时候。
On the, on Monday.
我想更详细的看看它。
And I want to look a little bit more in detail.
现在我们对锁有了更多的了解，
And now that we know a little bit more about locks
也说明了几个有趣的观点。
and then also illustrate a couple of interesting points.
首先，你想知道，
So first, you know it turns out you want to know,
查看锁，
what's looking at lock,
UART 只有一个锁，
it turns out that the uart actually has only one lock,
你可以认为这是一个可用的粗粒度（锁），
so you can think about this as a reasonable coarse-grained,
在一点上对于 UART 来说。
design at this particular point at least for uart.
这个锁保护 UART 传输缓冲区，
And that particular lock, it protects basically uart transmission buffer
以及写指针和读指针。
and write pointer and read pointer.
当我们传输的时候，
So when we transmit,
写指针指向传输缓冲区中的下一个空闲插槽，
you know the write pointer points to the next free slot in the transmission buffer
而读指针是需要传输的下一个插槽。
and the read pointer is the next slot that actually needs to be transmitted.
这就是我们并行的标准设计，
Maybe this is our standard design for parallelism,
或者是生产者消费者并行性。
or for a consumer, producer consumer parallelism.
让我回去，把它拿出来。
So let me go back and brought it out.
案例研究 UART ，
So, case study uart,
这是缓冲区，
and there's basically buffer,
有一个读指针，一个写指针，
and there's a read pointer, there's a write pointer
或者写索引和读索引。
or write read index and read index.
这是连接到用来显示的 UART ，
This has to go to uart being displayed,
这是写入端，
and this is the writer,
可能是 printf ，将字符插入到缓冲区中。
printf maybe that actually sticks characters into this buffer.
好的?
Okay?
所以，我们可以看到这个锁有多个作用。
And so you know we can see is that the lock, you know lock has multiple roles.
一个是保护这个数据结构，
One is to basically protect this data structure,
这个数据结构具有某种不变性，
this data structure has some invariance,
也就是，从读到写，
namely, the read to [proceed] write,
任何在 R 和 W 之间的字符都是要发送的，
anything between R and W are characters that need to be sent,
任何在 W 和 R 之间的东西都是空插槽。
anything between W and R are things that actually are empty slots.
这个锁帮助我们维持这个不变量。
And the locks are basically help us maintain that invariant.
所以，我们回到代码。
So, here are code again.
让我们看一下 acquire 。
And let's look at the acquire.
这里是 uartputc ，
So here's uartputc,
uartputc 做的第一件事是，
and you know the first thing you know uartputc [] does is,
获取锁，
actually you know grab the lock,
然后插入一个字符，
and then stick a character,
如果缓冲区中有位置，
if there's a place in the buffer,
将字符插入缓冲区，
sticks the [] character in the buffer
开始打印，
and start you know the printing
然后释放锁，
and then releases the lock,
所以，如果两个进程同时调用 uartputc ，
so if two processes at the same time call uartputc,
那么锁将会确保，
then there's lock will ensure that
第一个进程中的一个字符出现在第一个插槽中，
you know one character from the first process goes in the first slot
然后第二个进程的字符进入下一个插槽，
and then the second character of the second process goes into the next slot
它们不会最终进入同一个插槽。
and they're no as happened to end up in the same slot, right.
所以这是一个明显的例子，
So this is a clear example
锁可以帮助我们避免竞态条件，
where lock it helps us to avoids a race condition,
否则，第二个进程可能会
because otherwise you know the, the second process might
覆盖第一个进程的字符，
overwrite you know the first process's character,
这是一部分。
that's one part.
然后，我们看看。
Then we go look at.
我们之前看过一点，
And we did that a little bit before,
我们查看 start ，
we look at start,
我们看到有更多的事情。
we see a couple more things going on.
这个，我们看到，
The, we see actually that the,
如果缓冲区不是，
if buffer is not you know,
如果缓冲器不为空，
if the buffer is not empty,
那么我们知道有一些字符，
then we know that basically there's a bunch of characters,
正在进行或正在发送。
that are being progressed or being sent.
你知道锁可以确保，
And you know the lock you know make sure that
我们不会覆盖其中的任何一个，
we don't really overwrite any of those,
所以任何队列尾端的东西，
so anything that's sort of the tailend of the queue,
是由 UART 本身处理的。
is actually being processed by the uart itself.
所以，尾端正在处理。
So, tailend is in flight.
我们确保，
And we make sure that
通过获取锁，我们不会在这个方面修改或干扰。
we basically don't modify or interfere with that particular aspect by grabbing a lock.
最后，更多的事情是，
And then finally, they're sort of more and more thing is that
对 UART 寄存器的写入，
the writes to registers of the uart
比如 THR 寄存器，
like that THR register,
这里只有一个锁确保，
which one, there's only one you know basically the lock ensures,
记得 uartstart 在持有锁的情况下调用，
remember the uartstart just called with lock held,
确保只有一个写入者到 THR 寄存器。
assures this is only one writer to the THR register.
所以，另一方面锁确保的是，
And so another in sort of variant or another aspect that the locking enforces is
硬件寄存器有一个写入者。
that hardware registers have one writer.
好的?
Okay?
还有一件有趣的事，
You know, there's one other interesting thing,
我想稍微谈一下，
that I want to talk a little bit about,
那就是 UART 硬件完成后，
and that is you know the uart is done correct, hardware is done,
会有一个中断。
then there was an interrupt.
如你所知，
And, as you know,
我们注意到在 uartstart 之前，
we notice before uartstart right,
我们有调用者，
you know we have the caller,
它是获取锁的调用者，
it's a caller to acquire the lock,
来确保，
to ensure that,
我们不会有多个[]写入写寄存器。
we don't multiple [] writing to the write register.
UART 中断本身可以
And so uart interrupt itself could
与调用 printf 的其他进程并行运行，
run in parallel with another process that's called printf,
所以，有一些实际的 printf 运行在 CPU0 上，
so there's some practical printf that runs on CPU0,
而在 CPU1 上接受 UART 中断，
and on CPU1 actually takes the uart interrupt,
因为它什么都没做，
because maybe it's doing nothing,
所以，它可以在任何时间点中断。
and so it's ready to interrupt any particular point of time.
它将会调用 uartstart 。
And it will call uartstart.
它必须是这种情况，
And it has to be the case correct,
我们希望确保硬件寄存器中只有一个写入者，
you know we want to ensure that there's a single writer into the hardware registers
或者保护传输缓冲区的不变性，
or to protect you know the invariance actually of the transmission buffer,
我们必须获取锁。
you know we have to acquire a lock.
所以，在 xv6 中，
And so it is the case that in xv6,
中断可以运行驱动的下半部，
actually that interrupts you know can run the bottom half of the driver
可以在不同的处理器上真正的同时运行，
can run truly concurrent on on different processors
和驱动的上半部一起，
with the top half of the driver
所以，中断函数也需要锁。
and so therefore interrupt functions also require locks.
实际上，在这种情况下，
In fact, in this particular case,
需要在 UART 中的锁，
you know requires the one lock that there's actually in the uart
然后调用 uartstart ，
and then calls uartstart
然后释放锁。
and then releases the lock.
稍后，我会回到这里，
And I'll come back to that in a second,
因为实现锁比较困难，
because there's a little bit trickiness in implementing a lock,
在这种方式下，这是正确的。
in such a way that this actually works out correctly.
你应该担心的事情是，
And, and the thing that actually you should be worried about is that,
稍后我会讲一下，
I'll actually talk about in a second,
等到了那里我再讲。
let me postpone that until I get there.
好的，关于这个，有什么问题，
Okay, so any any questions about this,
一个简单的使用锁和 UART 的例子。
sort of simple example of lock use and uart.
好的，让我来讲一下，
Okay, let me that thing kind of,
让我来讲一下实现锁。
let me talk about implementing a lock.
所以，规范是只有一个进程可以获取锁，
So the spec is that only one process can acquire lock,
在任何时间点锁持有者都不会超过一个。
there's no more than one lock holder at any given point of time.
我们想要了解，
And we want to look and understand
如何实现锁，
actually how you implement a lock
以保证规范的方式。
in such a way that actually is guaranteed.
我会先写一个错误的锁，
Let me first write a broken lock,
让我们理解这里的挑战是什么，
so we understand you know what the challenge is
或者错误的 acquire 。
or broken acquire.
这样，我们知道挑战是如何实现 acquire 。
So that we know what the challenge is actually an implement acquire.
这是我的错误的那个，
So here's my broken one,
acquire struct lock *l ，
so, struct [] acquires lock *l,
它所做是，
you know what it does is
在它后面，有一个无限循环 while(1) ，
it follows, it has an infinite loop while(1),
如果 l->locked 是零，表示没有人持有它。
you know if l is locked is zero mean nobody holding it.
然后，调用者应该获取锁，
Then, presumably the caller should grabbed the lock,
那么，我们把 l->locked 设为 1 ，
so, then we set l->locked to one,
在这个时刻我们拿到了锁，
and you know at that point we got the lock,
我们可以返回，
so we can return,
什么事情都不用做，
nothing to do anymore,
并结束循环。
and close loop.
如果我们没拿到锁，
If we didn't get the lock,
因为 locked 是 1 ，
because the locked was one,
这意味着有其他人持有锁，
it means somebody else is holding lock,
我们只需要继续旋转，
so we just keep spinning,
等待一遍又一遍地循环，
waiting to go around the loop over and over and over
直到在某一时刻，锁持有者调用 release ，
until at some point you know the holder, lock holder called release,
它会将 locked 设置为零。
which will set lock to, will set lock to zero.
那么这个实现的问题是什么？
And you know what's wrong with this particular implementation?
我想两个进程可能同时读到它没有被锁。
I think two processes may read that it's not locked at the same time.
是的，没错。
Yeah right.
所以，这里有一个竞态条件，
So there's a race condition here
竞态条件在这里。
and just to make sure the races right here.
我们可以有两个 CPU 进来。
We can have basically two CPUs coming in.
我们看这个时序图，
You know we talk time diagram,
你知道 CPU1 ， CPU0 ， CPU1 ，
you know CPU1, CPU0, CPU1,
这是语句 A，
you know this statement A,
这是语句 B ，
maybe this statement B,
CPU1 到达语句 A ，
both CPU1 you know reach statement A,
CPU0 和 CPU1 都到达语句 A ，
CPU0 and CPU the zero one both reach statement A,
所以，它们都看到 locked 是零，
so they both see locked being zero
然后，它们都执行了 B 。
and then they're both execute B.
好的，这里它们看到 locked 是 0 ，
Alright, so here they see locked zero,
这个也看到的是 locked 是 0 。
this guy see locked zero.
所以，它们都执行语句 B ，
And so they both executes statement B,
它们都获得了锁，
both have acquired lock
那么这个函数违反了规范。
and which violated the spec, you know this particular function.
这能理解吗？
This makes sense?
所以，要解决这个问题，
So it turns out you know to solve this problem
并得到一个正确的实现，
and sort of get a correct implementation,
有多种方式可以做到，
there are multiple ways of going about it,
但最常见的方式是依靠特殊的硬件指令。
but the most common ways to rely basically on a special hardware instruction.
这条硬件指令所做的就是，
And hardware instruction that basically what it does,
它做这个测试，并原子的设置。
it does this test and then set atomically.
所以，解决这个问题的方法是
And so solution to this problem is
硬件的 testandset 支持。
hardware testandset support.
你可以这样想，
And the way you can think about it,
在 RISC-V 上，
you know on the RISC-V,
这条指令是 amoswap ，
you know this instruction actually there's the amoswap,
是我们会用到的。
that would gonna be using.
基本上可以归结为测试和设置，
And basically boils down to test and set,
硬件保证，
basically the hardware guarantees,
你使用这三个参数，
you will take this, takes two arguments or three arguments,
地址，寄存器一 r1 和寄存器二，寄存器1 R1和寄存器2
address, register one r1 and register two
本质上硬件所做的是，
and essentially what the hardware does conceptually is,
它锁定这个地址，
it locks the address,
如果你愿意，我们稍后会更多的讨论锁定地址。
if you will, we'll talk about that in a second little bit more locks address.
它（把值）放入一个临时变量，
It, it puts in a temporary variable,
那个地址中的值。
you know the value that actually is at that particular address.
然后，将 r1 的值放到地址中。
And then, raise the value of r1 into the address.
然后把原始地址的值放入，
And then basically puts the value that was at the originally address into,
tmp 中的原始值放入 r2 ，
temp- temporary value, that was the original value was actually address actually into r2
然后释放锁，并返回。
and then basically unlocks and returns.
在这个锁里，
And you know in this lock,
你能保证这个测试，
you will guarantee is that basically this test,
测试结果会返回到 r2 ，
where the result of the test is returned into r2
而设置是原子发生的。
and the set actually happened atomically.
所以这是一条硬件指令，
And so this is a hardware instruction,
大多数处理器都有这样的硬件指令。
most processor have an hardware instruction like this.
因为这是一种方便的实现锁的方法。
Because it's a convenient way to actually implement locks.
所以我们要做的是，
So basically what we've done is,
我们减少软件锁实现原子性，
like we've reduced the atomicity of this software lock implementation,
而是硬件锁实现。
to basically a hardware lock implementation.
处理器可能会使用不同的方式实现这个，
And so the processor might implement this in very different ways,
所以，指令集本身有一份说明书，
so basically the instruction set itself, there's like a specification,
它并没有说明它是如何实现的，
it doesn't actually say how it's implemented
它非常依赖于实际的实现。
and it is very dependent on the actual implementation.
显然取决于内存系统的工作方式。
Obvious, dependent on how the memory system exactly works.
比如，如果多个处理器共享单个内存控制器，
So, for example, if you know the multi processor shared single memory controller,
对内存进行读写，
that reads or writes to memory,
那么内存控制器可以支持该操作，
then the memory controller can actually support this operation,
允许在一个特定的地址设置锁，
basically allow you to lock in a particular address,
然后让一个处理器做两个操作或三条指令，
you know and then let you know one processor do two operations or three instructions
然后解锁，
and then [] will unlock
因为所有处理器的读写都通过这个内存控制器，
and so since all the processors reads or writes go for this memory controller,
内存控制器可以对锁进行排序。
the memory controller can do the ordering of locking.
如果处理器中的内存位于共享总线上，
If the memories are in this processor are sitting on a shared bus,
通常是总线仲裁器可以做这个，
it's often the bus arbiter that can actually do that,
总线仲裁器支持以原子方式执行两条内存操作。
where bus arbiter has support for basically executing two memory operations in an atomic way.
如果处理器有缓存，
If it's, if the processor have caches,
那么它通常是高速缓存一致性协议的一部分，
then, it's sort of typically part of the cache coherence protocol,
高速缓存一致性协议将确保，
where cache coherence protocol will ensure that
如果有写入者，
if there's a writer,
缓存行会持有我们要更新的值，
you know that that particular cache line that holds a value we want to update,
最终在一个单独的高速缓存中，
ends up in one single cache,
然后，处理器控制有两个操作的单个缓存行的锁。
and then basically the processor is control of lock that single cache line across two operations.
所以，这个的实现，
So the implementation of this,
可以用多种不同的方式来完成，
you know can be done in many different ways,
但理论上来说，
but conceptually the,
所做的是，你锁定地址，
what's going on, it's like you lock the address,
读取原始值，
you read your original value,
保存新值，
you store in the new value
然后返回值。
and you return your value.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
看看我们如何使用这条指令，
To see how we can use that instruction,
让我们看看 xv6 中 acquire 和 release 的实现，
let's actually look at the implementation of acquire and release in xv6
它还会揭露一些其他有趣的细节。
and it will expose a couple of other interesting details.
让我先来介绍一下 spinlock.h ，
So let me first bring up spinlock.h,
spinlock.h ，如你所见，它非常简单，
spinlock.h, as you can see, it's pretty straightforward,
它有这个 locked 标记，和我们的伪代码一样，
it has this flag locked, exactly as in our pseudo code
还有其他两个东西用来调试，
and then there's two other things for debugging,
即锁的名称，
namely the name of the lock
和当前持有锁的 CPU 。
and the CPU, the last, the current CPU that actually holding the lock.
这主要是打印出调试消息，
And this is mostly to print out the debugging messages,
比如，获取相同的 CPU 。
for example you do to acquire some of the same CPU.
好的，让我们来看看它的实现。
Okay, so then let's look at the implementation.
我们从 acquire 开始。
And so let's start out with acquire.
我们先看看这个循环，
And let's first look at this loop,
这实际上是一种测试和设置循环，
so this is actually the sort of test and set loop,
就是我刚才谈到的，
that I just talked about,
实际上，在 C 标准中，
it turns out that in the C standard,
定义了这些原子操作之一，
actually defines one of these atomic operations
C 标准种有一个函数，
and so C standard actually has a function,
也就是 __sync_lock_test_and_set ，
that says you know __sync_lock_test_and_set
指定了我刚才描述的行为。
and basically specifies the behavior that I just described.
然后，每个处理器都需要实现该行为，
And then every processor basically required to implement that behavior
由于大多数处理器具有测试和设置硬件指令，
and since most processors have and matching of test and set hardware instruction,
这是实现[]的一个合理而直接的方案，
this turns out to be a reasonable straightforward for the [] to implement,
实际上，如果我们看看 kernel.asm ，
then so in fact if we look at kernel.asm,
我们可以查看汇编指令，
we can look at the assembly instructions
了解 RISC-V 处理器的确切功能。
and see exactly what the RISC-V processor does.
所以。
So.
这是我们的汇编结构 acquire ，
At here is our assembly structures acquire
这是 amoswap 指令。
and let's here's our amoswap instruction.
所以你可以看到，
So you can see,
amoswap 调用寄存器 a5 ，
if you know amoswap basically called register a5
并且输入和输出也是 a5 ，
and the input and output also ends up in a5
与整个地址一样长，
and as long as the whole [] address
如果不相等，我们就返回，
and if it's not equal, we return
否则我们会回到，
and otherwise basically we go back to, we jump back to,
再检查一遍我说的是对的，
double check I'm saying the right thing here,
将 a4 移动到[]，
move a4 [],
如果不等于，则到 +0x22 。
if not equal to 0x twenty plus 22.
好吧，这有点难计算，
Alright, that's a little hard to calculate,
但基本上在一种情况下，我们[扩展]，
but basically in one case, we branch out
在另一种情况下，我们向后分支。
and in the other case, we [branch back].
所以，可能看 C 代码更容易。
So this may be easier to look at the C code.
所以让我们到这里，
So let's go away in here,
那么会发生什么呢，
so what happens,
如果锁没有被持有，
so if the if the lock is not held,
lk->locked 的值是多少，
what will be the value of l lock,
lk->locked 会是零，
well lk->locked will be zero right,
所以我们称之为测试和设置，
and so we call this test and set,
将会发生的是，我们在 locked 中写入 1 ，
what will happen is we'll write one in locked,
但是返回之前的值。
but return the previous value.
所以如果之前的值是零，
So if the previous value is zero,
那我们就好了，
then we're good right,
因为这意味着没有人拿着锁，
because that means that nobody was holding the lock
我们就结束了这个 while 循环。
and we fall through and we're done with this while loop.
现在，我们假设锁的值是 1 ，
Now, let's say the lock value was one,
所以可能锁已经上锁，
so probably the lock actually locked,
这条指令会做什么，
well, what will this instruction do,
它会读取旧值，把它放在一边，
it will read the old value, put that in the side correct,
在这种情况下，是 1 ，
there's one in this case
然后在那个位置写入一个新的 1 。
and then write a new one into that location.
这不会改变任何事情，
And that will change nothing right,
因为它已经被锁上了。
because it was already locked.
函数将会返回 1 ，
And and the function will return one,
表明之前的持有，
indicating that actually some of the previous hold,
它已经被锁上了，
that it was already locked
所以在这种情况下，它不等于零，
and so in that case it's unequal to zero
它会旋转，一直旋转，
and it will spin, will keep spinning
直到 locked 重新设置为 0 ，
until locked actually set back to zero,
而这发生在 release 中。
and presumably happened in this release.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
没有问题？
No questions?
好的。
Okay.
所以现在，让我们看看对应的 release 操作，
So now basically you know let's look at the corresponding the release operation,
这里是 release 操作，
And, and here's release operation,
如果你再看一下 kernel.asm 。
and if you look at the kernel.asm again.
那个指令，
That instruction,
所以让我们看看 release ，
so lets look at release,
可能在这里后面，这是 release 。
probably right after, here release.
所以， release 也使用了这个 amoswap 指令，
So the release actually also uses this amoswap instruction,
把 0 放入 s1 。
and putting basically zero into s1.
所以这保证的是，
And so this guarantee is
这个原子更新 lk->locked ，
basically that this atomic update you know to l->locked or lk->locked,
使用原子操作将 0 写入 lk->locked 。
writing zero into lk->locked using atomic operation.
你们中的许多人问到，为什么不直接使用 store ，
Many of you ask why not just use store,
store 指令来写入 0 。
store instruction to actually write zero.
有没有人，能猜猜为什么，
Anybody, may you want to guess why,
为什么那可能行不通，
why that might not work
或者问题可能是什么。
or what the problem could be.
因为某个其他进程可能正在将 1 写入锁，或者，
Because then some other process might be writing one to the lock or,
不，或者再写一个 0 ，
no, or writing another zero,
但不是这样的，对吧。
but that can't be the case, right.
是啊，可能是对的，
Yeah, well there could be okay,
可能有两个进程或两个 CPU 同时写入 l->locked ，
so there could be two processes or two CPUs writing to l->locked at the same time right,
但我认为真正的问题是，
but I think what the question really is that,
对很多人来说，我也经常这么想，
you know, for many people and I often assume this too,
就是你要做一条 store 指令，
is that you're going to do a single store instruction,
这是一个原子操作。
that is sort of like an atomic operation.
并不总是这样的，
There's not always the case,
比如，如果你，
for example if you are
这取决于架构的实现，
and it really depends on the architecture implementation,
比如，如果缓存[]协议工作，
like for example if the cache [] protocol works
或者缓存系统使用缓存行工作，
or cache system works using cache lines,
其中缓存行可能大于整数，
where cache line maybe bigger than integer,
通常大于整数，
are typically bigger than integer,
那么真正发生的是，
then really what's happening is,
第一个操作是加载缓存行，
that the first operation is loading the cache line,
然后是更新缓存行，
and then updating the cache line,
所以， store 指令里面有两个微操作，
so in fact you know store instruction, basically has two micro operations in it
你可能会得到错误的结果。
and you can get the wrong result.
所以，为了避免必须了解任何硬件实现，
So, you know to avoid you know having to understand anything of the hardware implementation,
以及整数运算是否是原子的，
of exactly and whether integer operations are atomic or not
或者写入 64 位内存值是原子操作，
or writing to 64 bit 64 bit memory values as atomic operation,
我们使用 RISC-V 操作，
you know we use the RISC-V operation,
它可以保证原子执行。
that is guaranteed to be executed atomically.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
是的。
Yes.
好的，为了[扩展]一下，
Okay, so just, just for your [amusement],
amoswap 不是唯一存在的指令，
amoswap is not the only instruction that exists,
这是 RISC-V 手册，
so here's the RISC-V manual,
在列表中，是所有的原子操作，
in lists, whole bunch of the atomic operation,
所以有 AMOAND, AMOOR ，
so there's an amoand, amoor,
还有 AMOMAX, AMOMIN ，
there's max min,
它们都可以在原子操作中读写一个值。
they're all can read or write a value in an atomic operation.
好的?
Okay?
好的，还有其他几件事我想指出，
Okay, so there's a couple other things, I want to point out,
在这个实现中。
in this particular implementation.
让我重新回到 acquire 。
In, let me start again go back to acquire.
所以， acquire 函数首先做的是，
So one of the first things that the acquire function does is
它关闭了中断。
it turns off interrupts.
最好能理解为什么是这样，
And it's really good to understand why that is the case
现在，我回到 UART 示例代码。
and so for now I'm gonna go back to uart example code.
你可以稍微想一想这个。
And you think a little bit about this.
所以我们要考虑一下这个情况，
And so we want to think about the case,
是 acquire 可能没有正确实现，
were acquire is actually maybe incorrectly implemented,
没有关闭中断，
does not turn off interrupts,
所以思考这个问题的方法是，
so the way to think about this is
如果我们到 uartputc ，
if we go to uartputc,
我们假设 uartputc 运行，
and here let's say uartputc runs,
并且获得了锁，
and acquires the lock,
但是不关闭中断，
and but does not turn off interrupts,
会发生什么。
what can happen.
给大家几秒钟考虑一下，
Give everybody a couple seconds to think about it,
如果你有想法
if you have an idea
或者为什么它可能是错误的，
or why it might be wrong,
可以直接说。
like jumpin.
或许，它可以被中断，
Perhaps, it could be interrupted,
因为时钟，然后其他事情发生了，
because of, because of the clock and then something happens
它也需要打印一些其他的东西，
and it needs to print something else,
它试图再做一次 uartputc ，
and it tries to do uartputc again,
但是锁已经被拿走了。
but the lock is already taken.
这是一种可能的情况，
That might be a possible scenario,
有一个更直接的例子。
there is a much more direct example for this.
我们假设 uartputc 得到了锁，
So let's say uartputc grab the lock
而 UART 正忙于传输一些字符。
and uart were busy transmitting some character.
那么当 UART 完成了传输字符，
So when uart done or transmitting character,
它要做什么。
what does it do.
它会导致中断，
It causes an interrupt correct
并且 uartintr 运行，
and uartintr runs,
uartintr 会做什么，
what uartintr do,
它获取同一把锁，
it grabs the same lock,
uartputc 已经持有了，
you know that the uartputc is holding right,
那么，这里会发生什么，
so what will happen here,
如果只有一个 CPU ，
if there's only one CPU
没有其他 CPU 可以运行这个中断。
and so there's no other CPU where this interrupt could be running.
我们现在死锁了，
Well, we have a deadlock right,
因为当前 CPU 持有 uartputc 的锁，
because the current CPU is holding the lock as part of uartputc,
然后，后面传入的中断，
then later the interrupt that came in
它做的第一件事就是，
and the first thing it tries to do is
获取已经持有的锁。
actually acquire a lock has already held.
实际上，在 xv6 的情况下，你会得到一个 panic ，
In fact, in the case of xv6, you will get a panic,
因为相同的 CPU ，
because you know the same CPU,
正在再次尝试获取相同的锁。
is actually trying to acquire the same lock again.
所以，获得自旋锁，
So basically you know what acquire spinlock,
处理了两种不同类型的并发，
deals with sort of two different types of concurrency,
其一，它们是两个不同 CPU 之间的并发，
one they're sort of concurrency between two different CPUs,
而且我们必须保证，
and we get make sure like for example is
中断函数运行在不同的 CPU 上，
the interrupt function runs on a different CPU,
一般我们不会重新安排传输缓冲区，
you know basically we're don't get arrange on the transmission buffer,
但是如果它们在同一个 CPU 上运行，
but if they run in the same CPU,
我们要确保它仍然是原子的，
we're going to make sure that it's still atomic
它不会被中断，
and that is not being interrupted
所以，我们在 acquire 中关闭了中断。
and therefore we actually turn the interrupts off in acquire.
它们只有在 release 结束时才会再次打开，
And they're only turned on again at the end of release,
当锁被释放的时候，
when the lock actually has been released,
在这一点上，再次看到，
at that point is see it again,
接收中断，
you know to take these interrupts,
因为锁不会再被释放，
because lock actually is not released anymore,
不是 acquire 持有它，不再持有。
not acquire holding it, not held anymore.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，在这个实现中还有一件更微妙的事情，
Okay, there's one more subtle thing in this implementation,
我想说一下，
that I want to talk about,
而且我们需要处理。
and we need to deal with.
那就是内存排序。
And that is memory ordering.
比如，你认为锁是，
So for example you think about lock is,
比如， acquire locked 是 1 ，
let's say, acquires its locked to one,
也许我们有一个临界区，
maybe we have a critical section,
x<-x+1 ，
in which you x x plus one
然后， release 将 locked 设置为 0 。
and then acquire release you know set locked zero.
所以，考虑一下指令方案，
So you know sort of think about instruction scheme,
它是在特定的 CPU 上执行的，
that's being executed on a particular CPU,
这些是正在执行的指令。
you know so these are the instructions are being executed, right.
现在，如果代码仅仅是顺序的。
Now, if the code were just purely sequential.
编译器或处理器可能会重新排序指令，
The compiler or the processor could actually reorder instructions,
为了获得更好的性能，
you know just to get better performance,
比如，如果它是顺序流，
for example, if it were a sequential stream,
可以把这个指令移到后面去吗？
would it be okay to move this instruction to afterwards.
我们不会改变单一执行流程的正确性。
We don't change the correctness of the single stream of execution.
你知道，不是很清楚，
You know, not really,
因为锁是完全独立的，
because lock the next are totally independent of each other,
与它无关，
there's no relation to it,
如果是顺序执行就完全没问题，
would be perfectly fine if it were a sequential execution,
将 x 移动到 locked 0 之后。
that the x has moved after locked zero.
所以，在单一的串行执行中，
So that you know on the single, single serial execution,
这是对的。
that's okay.
实际上，处理器都是这样做的，
And in fact and in fact processors you know do this all the time,
它们[]地执行任务，
you know they do [] execute stuff,
我们期望执行指令，
we're expected to execute instructions
这会导致这些指令重新排序。
and so that can result in basically these instructions re-orderings.
编译器也会这样做，
The compiler does it too,
可能优化一些代码路径，
may be optimized some code path
并且重新排序指令，
and also will reorder instructions,
结果是相同的串行执行。
as long as you know results in the same serial execution.
但是，很明显在并行执行的过程中这是一场灾难，
But clearly during concurrent execution this be disaster, right,
因为如果获取了锁，
because if lock are acquire,
这是我们的 release ，
and this was our release,
我们所做的，
and basically what we've done,
我们将临界区间移出了 acquire 区间，
we move the critical section outside of the the acquire region,
这完全是错误的。
that would be totally incorrect.
所以，这在并发执行中是错误的。
So that's wrong, wrong in a concurrent execution.
所以，为了禁止或告诉编译器和硬件不要这么做，
And so you know to forbid or tell the compiler and hardware not to do this,
有一个叫做内存屏障的东西，
there's something that's called memory fence
或者某个 synchronize ，
or something that synchronize,
这个指令表示，
there's instructions basically says,
在这个点之前的加载或保存，
like any loads or stores before this point,
不允许移动到这一点之后。
you are not allowed to move beyond this point.
所以 release 有这个， acquire 也有这个，
And so release has this and acquire has this
比如，这个 x<-x+1 ，
and so for example, this x plus, x plus one,
如果这个更新是在 acquire 之后和 release 之前，
if that was updated after the acquire and before the release,
x<-x+1 必须留在，
the x plus x plus one has to stay
这个内存同步点之前。
before you know this particular memory synchronization point.
所以不会，
And so it will not be,
不会有内存重排的问题，
there will be no trouble with memory ordering,
这就是 __sync_synchronize 在这的原因，
so this is the reason why __sync_synchronize there,
无论是在 release 还是在 acquire 。
both in the release and also there's one in the acquire.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
我有一个问题。
I have a question.
是不是按照惯例，
Is it, is it by convention
这个[]的开始，
that the start of the [],
所以，我想编译器可以搞清楚，
so I guess I guess the the compiler could figure out,
在获取锁之前，有一条指令，
that there is an instruction before the lock is even acquire
它可以被移动到锁释放之后。
and that it can be just as well moved after the lock is released.
这会发生吗，
Can that happen,
或者它会遇到屏障。
or will it encounter a barrier and see that.
在这种情况下，
You will see, you know in this case,
acquire 是一个屏障，
acquire as a barrier
release 也是一个屏障，
and release as a barrier,
所以，任何在 locked 设置为 1 之前发生的事情，
so anything that happened before locked is set to one
会在它之前发生，
will happen before that,
永远不会超过那个指令，
it will never pass that instruction,
这就是屏障，
so this is a barrier,
如果你愿意的话，
if you will,
这个是屏障一，这是屏障二。
this barrier one, and this is barrier two.
所以，这意味着在这之前的任何指令，留在这里，
And so it means that any instruction before here, stay here,
在之间的指令，会发生在 acquire 和 release 之间，
any instruction between what happened between the two between acquire and release
之后的指令，将留在 release 之后。
and instruction after will stay after the release.
好的。
Okay.
好的?
Okay?
好的，我的时间快到了，
Okay so I'm running close to the end,
所以让我来总结一下。
so let me just actually wrapup here.
所以，对于锁，锁对正确性有好处，
So, to locks, you know locks are good for correctness,
但可能会对性能造成不良影响。
but can be bad for performance.
这是一种失望的局面，
Which sort of a bummer correct,
因为我们使用锁的一个原因是，
because we are one reason we actually got into locks is
为了在并行执行过程中保持正确，
basically to get correct during parallel execution,
但是锁实际上限制了并行执行。
but locks actually limit parallel execution.
这是一个或两个锁使编程复杂化。
That's one and two locks complicate programming.
你会在一些实验里体验到，
And you will experience that in some of the lab,
从现在开始，我们将要做的事情，
that we're going to be doing, in fact from now on,
我们会看到锁一直会出现，
we'll see lock shown all the time,
这至少会给我们一些思考，
and that will give us least you know some thought,
有必要理解为什么锁在那里，
you know it's going to be necessary to understand why the locks are there
以及它们保护的是什么。
and what they protect.
如果你做并行编程，这是一种内在的，
And there sort of inherent, if you do parallel programming,
你需要使用锁。
that you need to use locks.
所以，如果你想避免锁带来的复杂性，
And so you know if you want to avoid the complications due to locks,
你可以做几件事，
you know a couple things you could do,
不要分享它，除非必须这么做。
you know don't share it, you don't have to.
如果你没有共享数据结构，
If you don't have shared data structures,
这些竞态条件就不会发生，
these race conditions cannot happen,
所以这里你不需要锁，
and so there and so you you don't need locks
你不需要这种复杂的编程。
and so you don't need this complicated programming.
但是，通常你会有一些共享的数据结构，
But you know typically you will have some shared data structures,
你会需要锁，
you will do, you will need locks
我认为要做的事情是从粗粒度开始，
and I think the thing to do is start with coarse-grained,
然后在需要的时候转向细粒度，
and then move to fine-grained if necessary
基于你的测量，
based on your measurements,
你要确保锁真的争用，
you want to make determined to make sure that the lock actually contended,
在你开始重新设计之前。
before you actually start redesigning.
最后，也可以使用竞争检测器。
And finally, you know use a race detector to.
这些竞争检测器工具会发现问题或竞态条件，
And one of these race detector tools actually finds problems or race conditions,
因为你把锁放错了，
because you put the locks in the wrong
或者你将 acquire 和 release 放错了，
or you put the acquire and release in the wrong place
而实际上，你还有竞争。
and in fact you still have races.
好的，这是一个关于锁的快速介绍，
Okay so there's a quick introduction to locks,
我们将会谈论更多关于锁的话题，
we're going to talk a lot more about locks
在本学期的剩余课程中，
in the basically for the rest of the semester,
它会出现，
that will show up,
最后，我们将讨论有关无锁编程的问题，
and we'll talk a little bit more about lock-free programming at the end
看看在内核中是如何做到这一点的。
and see how that's done in kernels.
好的，我在这里停止，
Okay, so let me stop here,
所以，任何必须去别的地方的人可以去，
so that anybody who has to go somewhere else can go,
但是，如果你还有什么问题，
but if you have any more questions,
请随时提出来。
feel free, please feel free to ask them.
我们在聊天中有个问题，
We have a question in the chat,
fence 指令是不是没有必要，
isn't the fence instruction unnecessary,
因为 amoswap 指令可以具有获取释放顺序。
because the amoswap instruction can have the acquire release ordering.
是的，好的，所以有两件事，
Yeah, okay, so okay, so two things,
sync 指令同时为编译器和硬件。
the sync instruction there both for the compiler and for the hardware.
是的，我马上要超过工作时间了，
Yeah I'm jumping off to sort of office hours,
但我认为还有更多的问题。
but I think there's still more questions in the.
如何只为编译器做这件事呢？
How do you do it for the compiler only?
编译器知道正在编译的是哪个体系结构，
The compiler knows which architecture is compiling
所以我们知道它什么时候必须确保合适的栅栏，
and so we will know when it actually has to ensure the appropriate fences
无论运行在哪种体系结构上，
for whatever architecture is running on
不管是哪种内存一致性模型。
and whatever memory consistency model it has.
所以这会引起更复杂的讨论，
So this gets a little bit more complicated discussion
就是每个硬件都有一个内存模型，
is that every piece of hardware has a memory model
编译器决定，
and the compilers decide
给特定架构的内存模型，
you know given the memory model for that particular architecture,
它可以做什么，不能做什么。
what actually can do what it cannot do.
我想我的问题是，
I guess my question was that
fence 指令只有在这种情况是没有必要的，
like the fence instruction only becomes unnecessary,
如果你调用 amoswap.w.rl ，
if you call amoswap like .w.rl,
放在 sync 中，这有一个 sync ，
and like putting in the the sync and there that will sync,
但是编译器排序，然后。
but the you know the compiler ordering and then the.
是的。
Yeah.
内存排序和无序。
The memory ordering and the out of ordering.
是的。
Yeah.
机器也使用 fence 指令，
Machinery using the fence instruction as well,
fence 指令只在执行 .rl 的情况下是没有必要的，
the fence instructions only unnecessary in the case that you do .rl,
看起来它不会检测到这一点，
so it seems like it wouldn't detect that,
那么你怎么做的，
so how would you do it,
所以编译器最终强制排序，
so the compiler enforces the ordering on its end,
但你已经使用[]指令覆盖了它。
but you already cover it using the [] instruction.
是的，好问题，
Yeah, you very good question,
更复杂的需求实现会是，
and you know more sophisticated requirements implementation would be,
比如 RISC-V 专门的 acquire 和 release 实现，
we were like specialized acquire and release implementation or implementation for RISC-V,
可能比我们做的事情更复杂，
you know probably do more sophisticated things than we do,
使用 fence 指令是一个粗粒度的实现。
pretty coarse grain by just issuing the fence instruction.
但是这有点复杂，
The, the but it's slightly complicated,
是的，如果你对这个感兴趣，
yeah, so if you're interested in this,
RISC-V 的内存模型非常复杂，
the memory model for RISC-V is really complicated,
如果你看一下操作手册中的非特权指令，
so if you look at the instruction manual for the unprivileged instructions,
有一整章来专门介绍内存排序，
there is whole chapter dedicated to memory ordering
告诉你应该做什么。
and tells you what they have to,
在特定情况下，编译器应该怎么做。
the compiler should do in this particular case.
所以，你的意思是编译器会注意到这一事实，
So you're saying that the compiler would pick up on the fact,
我们只是把汇编指令放在这里，
that we just put that assembly instruction inside of there,
而且它本身不会对任何内存访问进行重新排序。
and it wouldn't reorder any of the memory accesses on its own.
抱歉， synchronize ，这个同步库函数是库函数，
Sorry, the synchronize this, this synchronized library function is a library function right,
它可以通过不同的方式实现。
it can be implemented in different ways.
这是一种实现。
And this is one particular implementation.
并且库函数由编译器提供。
And the library function is provided by the compiler.
但是编译器有没有进行优化的选项，
But is there like the option for the compiler to do optimization,
它可以移动加载和存储指令。
where it itself moves the loads and stores around.
是的，编译器有。
Yes, compilers do.
那么如何在不使用 fence 指令时防止这种情况发生，
So how do you prevent that without emitting the fence instruction,
我想知道这个。
that's curious about.
我想我说的是，
I guess what I'm saying is that,
也许我想说的是，
and maybe what I'm saying is that basically the,
synchronized 告诉编译器和硬件，
this indication the synchronized basically both tells the compiler and hardware,
但是编译器可以实现不同的 __sync_synchronize ，
but the compiler could actually implement __sync_synchronize differently,
它知道它不能移动东西，
it knows that it can't move things around,
但它没有 RISC-V 上的发布和 fence 指令，
but it doesn't have the issue and fence instruction on the RISC-V,
它知道它以一种特殊的方式在 RISC-V 上运行。
it knew that it was running in a particular way on RISC-V.
但是 RISC-V 内存模型还不够吗，
But isn't the RISC-V memory model like [] enough
机器可以重组东西，
to where the out of order machinery could reorganize stuff,
所以你是否需要 acquire ，
so do you need like the acquire,
整个[点]都有。
it's like the whole point of having.
好的，还有比 __sync_synchronize 更复杂的接口，
Okay, there more complicated interfaces __sync_synchronize,
这给了编译器编写者更多的自由，
and which give the compiler writer more gives the programmer more freedom
我们可以得到编译器，
and we'll get the compiler
并将编译器和处理器解耦。
and decouple the compiler part and the processor part.
比如，我想这里有一个标记可以传入，
So, for example I think there's a flag you can pass in,
有一个 release 一致性同步。
you know to say that there's a release consistent synchronize.
我不知道细节，
You know I I don't know the details,
我不知道，
right out of my head,
但你可以查一下这个，
but you can look into this,
这是粗粒度接口，
this is the coarse-grained interface
更细粒度的接口，让程序员有更多的控制权。
and a more fine-grained interfaces that give the programmer more control.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thank you.
我有一个问题，
I have a question what is,
如果有多个线程和一个处理器，
how do you like for having multiple threads and one processor
[争论]的方式与我们对多处理器的争论是否相同。
do argue in roughly the same way as we did for multiple processors.
你能重复一下问题吗，只是确认一下。
Can you repeat that question just to make sure.
所以我们没有，
So we didn't,
我想我们并没有谈到多线程，
I think I don't think we really talked about multiple threads,
我们主要讨论的是多 CPU ，
we mostly talked about multiple CPUs,
所以对于多线程来说，
so for multiple threads is the,
我想解决方案与拥有多个 CPU 时的解决方案相同，
I guess the solution the same as for when you have multiple CPUs,
比如，那里有没有同样的参数。
like do you have the same arguments there.
或多或少，
More or less,
至少在理论上是正确的思考方式，
at least conceptually is the right way to think about it,
所以你有多个线程，
so you have multiple threads,
但是只有一个 CPU ，
but only one CPU,
还是这样情况，你希望确保，
it's still the case that you want to ensure
以原子方式执行某些内核代码序列。
that certain kernel code sequences are executed atomically.
所以，你仍然需要有一个临界区间的概念。
And so you still have to have a notion of critical sections.
你可能不需要显式的锁或释放，
You might not need locks or releases explicitly,
但是你确实需要一种打开和关闭中断的方法，
but you do need a way of turning on interrupts off and on
在一段代码中。
in a particular piece of code.
所以，如果你查看较旧的操作系统内核，
So if you look at older operating system kernels,
它们通常在内核中没有真正的锁获取，
they typically don't have really locking acquire in the kernel,
因为它们假设在一个处理器上运行，
because they assume they're running on a single processor,
但是它们确实有像锁这样的东西，
but they do have something like locks,
要打开和关闭中断。
you know to basically turn off interrupt and interrupt on and off.
好的，我明白了，
Okay I see,
我的另一个问题是，
and my other question was,
在带有 UART 图片和缓冲区的的幻灯片上。
actually on the slide with the uart picture, the buffer.
是的，是不是，
Yeah, is it,
是的，就是那个，
yeah that one,
是不是一直都是这样的，读在后面，
is it always the case that the read is going to be like lagging behind,
我不明白这个。
I didn't understand that.
是的，好的。
Yeah, okay so good.
所以这个到显示器，
So this goes to the display,
这是字符序列，
whatever is this basically this is the sequence of characters,
要到显示器。
that needs to go to the display.
写入者增加更多字符，
And the writer basically appending more and more characters, right.
所以，写入者走这条路，
And so, so the writers going that way
读取者跟随写入者，
and the readers, you know following the writer,
因为你不能打印尚未放入缓冲区的字符。
because you can't print a character that hasn't been put into buffer yet.
UART 把东西给显示器，
And so let's you know the the uart who puts things on the display,
开始将这个插槽中的第一个字符放到显示器上，
you know will start basically putting first characters in this slot onto the display,
同时， printf 进入，
meanwhile printf could come in multiple printf come in,
它们在这里放更多的字符，
you know they put more characters in here,
所以写指针在这里，
so that the write pointer spacing standing here
然后当显示了一个字符，
and then when there's one character is displayed,
然后 UART 将这个指针向上移动，
then the uart will move up this pointer
以显示下一个字符。
to display the next character.
UART 总是有点落后于写入者，
The uart is always lagging a little behind the writer,
直到它赶上，
until the point that it catches up right,
然后 r 和 w 相同，
then where r and w are the same,
在这一点上，意味着缓冲区中不再有字符。
and at that point, basically, that means that there's no character anymore in the buffer.
哦，好的，我明白了。
Oh okay I see, that makes, that makes a lot more sense.
好的，非常感谢。
Okay, thank you so much.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
还有什么问题吗？
Any more questions?
只有我们在这里。
Just us left here.
好的。
All right.
所有人，再见。
All you guys, see you later.